好的 接下來讓我們介紹的講者是Astrid
她將帶來KKBOX StoreKit migration 過渡作法
分享如何在新功能中導入StoreKit2
同時確保購買流程不受影響
特別提醒大家
如果還沒下載App或翻譯軟體的
可以掃badge後面的 QR code
因為接下來的議程要用英文分享
那讓我們歡迎 Astrid
Hello
I am Astrid
I'm here to show you how painful it is to implement In-App Purchase without RevenueCat
Just kidding.
I'm here to...
share my experience of introducing a new business model
Using StoreKit 2 in an app  that originally used StoreKit 1.
To tell you a bit about myself.
I've been an iOS developer at KKBOX for three and a half years.
And this is my first job, out of AppWorksSchool.
I am very grateful for the opportunity to be here.
I like being a developer,
because it feels great when people enjoy what I built.
Outside of work
I love playing with Tonku and traveling.
I just came back from Cambodia last month.
I enjoy learning how people live in different cultures.
Someday,
I hope to live abroad.
So far
many of you may have a question in your mind
Why is this person speaking English to a bunch of Taiwanese?
I was also inspired by try Swift Tokyo
This is a selfie from the after-party
We had developers from six different countries share ideas with common languages.
I hope iPlayground can grow into an event that attracts people from all around the world.
My English isn't perfect,
but I want to try
so that people who don’t understand Mandarin can engage more directly.
Also, I’m not an expert.
I'm just here to share my experience
and hopefully help some of you avoid the struggles I went through.
By the end of this talk
You’ll have a better idea of how to handle the challenges when using both StoreKit 1 and 2 in the same app.
Here's what I'll cover today:
A quick overview of StoreKit APIs
Our implementation context and strategic decisions
The technical challenges we faced
The tools we used for testing
The App Store review process reality
And key takeaways
Alright, let’s start with something fun.
Can I ask everyone  to raise your hand up?
Yes, everyone.
Thank you very much.
Now, Keep your hand up ...
if you know which In-App Purchase framework your company is  using
If you don't know,
just put your hand down.
I won’t tell your boss.. It's okay.
We still have many hands here.
Now, keep your hands up
If you're already started using StoreKit 2.
Wow
It's more than my imagination.
Okay
Thank you very much.
You can all put your hands down.
what I've seen
We don't have all people here starting using StoreKit 2 yet
which is great. It means this  talk is still useful for many  of you.
Now
let's start to see how StoreKit has evolved.
Actually, there’s no “official StoreKit 1.”
Its real name is...
Original API for In-App Purchase
but that’s a bit too long
So I’ll just call it StoreKit 1.
StoreKit 1 was introduced in 2009
It is delegate based
and requires manual management of the payment queue.
If you want to make a purchase
You have to make a payment with the product
And add the payment to the paymentQueue.
And there’s even more after that.
Don’t worry you don’t have to learn this
and hopefully you’ll never need to in your whole life
All I want to show is: StoreKit 1 is wordy and fragile.
StoreKit 2 came out in 2021
built on Swift Concurrency, making everything straightforward
If you want to make a purchase
just call product.purchase()
That's it
One single line, you get a result.
it’s fully scoped and type safe.
Sweet!
For receipt
StoreKit 1 gives you a unified receipt that
containing all purchases in the app,
you have to parse and validate yourself
StoreKit 2 provides Transaction objects
which contain productID, purchaseDate, and many other information.
Unlike StoreKit 1, StoreKit 2 allows you to directly access one transaction at a time.
It is much more easier to retrieve detailed information and customize your purchase flow
I used two examples to show how StoreKit2 provides easier and modern way to handle purchases.
Now, let’s move on to KKBOX implementation context.
For music streaming,
we use StoreKit 1 with the verifyReceipt API.
Both subscriptions types are supported
We didn’t have consumable product.
It works with our legacy billing system which only handles music transactions.
The system works reliably in production for many many years.
FanKlub
our new business model, works differently from music streaming
it uses consumable, built with Swift Concurrency.
And we have a new billing system that only handles FanKlub transactions.
With so many differences in logic and architecture
we needed to find an approach that cost the least development effort
To figure that out, we explored three options.
Option 1
Fully move to StoreKit 2.
But this is risky
Because it changes important parts of our app that have been stable for years
And you would need to have very close teamwork, with the billing and App team
The timeline is hard to predict, and it could delay the FanKlub launch
So option 2,
stay with StoreKit 1.
It sounds safer, but it actually has a big problem.
StoreKit 1 and the verifyReceipt API are already deprecated
Option 3
Hybrid approach!
and that’s the one we chose.
We use StoreKit 1 for music streaming and StoreKit 2 for FanKlub.
Apple allows mixing both API if we support iOS 15 or later, which we do.
This way, we can keep our stable legacy flow,
adopt StoreKit 2 for our new features
take advantage of Swift Concurrency
and reduce risk while preparing for a future migration.
To recap
StoreKit 2 provide a modern and easier way compared to StoreKit 1 to handle purchase
To balance stability and innovation, we chose a hybrid approach.
The trade-off is that now we have to maintain two flows, which means more complexity
Next, I’ll walk you through how we handle that.
Let’s start with a quick overview of how StoreKit handles transaction history
All transactions—whether using StoreKit 1 or StoreKit 2
are visible across both APIs
which means purchases made with StoreKit 1 can be accessed through StoreKit 2
and StoreKit 2 purchases also appear in the unified receipt used by StoreKit 1
This cross-visibility is intentional and documented by Apple
But when both APIs used in the same app, it requires careful handling to avoid duplicate processing.
So here comes the first problem.
StoreKit 1 receives updates from StoreKit 2 purchases—and vice versa
There’s no built in separation, which could easily lead to double-processing.
To fix this, we use productID to filter logic
All FanKlub productIDs contain fanKlub
In StoreKit 1
we skip fanKlub products
In StoreKit 2, we only handle fanKlub products.
filtering gives us a clear separation.
Problem 2.
Mixed Receipt Validation
StoreKit 1 gives you a unified receipt that contains all purchases in the app
So it contains music streaming and  FanKlub transactions
which our legacy billing system wasn't designed to handle that
To fix this,
we update our backend to ignore any transactions  related to FanKlub.
This way, the receipt upload won't break legacy logic.
Above challenges are the traits documented by Apple.
But there’s no document that covers all scenarios.
The tools provided by Apple really helped us a lot.
They affect In-App Purchase behavior whether we use StoreKit 1 or StoreKit 2
In the early development stage, we use StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
It doesn’t require internet or App Store Connect.
It’s like an offline playground
The testing configuration file provides many different options
that can remind you to handle scenarios that may happen.
In our case,
it reminded us to handle the “Ask to Buy” flow, which we hadn’t planned for
Once the flow is planned and built,
We use App Store sandbox with App Store Connect productID to test the flow
In this stage
we test both the legacy flow and the new FanKlub flow
including
sending sandbox receipts to our server.
Most of the issues with the app server are discovered and solved in this stage
In our case,
we found a FanKlub transaction inside the unified receipt
and when it was sent to our backend, it caused backend errors
Finally
we uploaded to TestFlight for internal testers to test the flow.
Because all transactions are in a sandbox environment for TestFlight reviewers
so people can test whatever they want without being charged
It helped us improve the user experience
Once everything was set up, we submitted our product to app review.
Normally, the review process is straightforward and doesn’t require any extra steps.
so we thought we were finally done
But then
Apple said
No.
It was really upsetting
I don't have...
I only have Mandarin screenshot, but I can read the message for you.
The In-App Purchase has been  rejected
For more information, refer to the App Review Notes
All productIDs showed: “Developer action needed.”
So, what happened?
Let’s refer to App Review Notes.
There are too many words here.
We can only focus on the key words.
Apple rejected our submission
because we introduced a new business model
moving from subscriptions to including consumable products
Apple wanted us to upload a new binary where FanKlub products are available to buy
But at that time,
only the purchase flow was implemented
All other FanKlub features were still in progress
We wondered
Would unlocking a placeholder feature be enough to pass review?
To be safe,
we waited and resubmitted after the full feature was ready.
Before resubmission
We confirm with our backend which APIs needed to go live in production
We also enabled our billing system to handle the  sandbox transactions
because initially, our production backend ignored sandbox transactions
We also recorded a demo video showing the full purchase flow
with detailed explanation
And shared it with the App Review Notes
Finally, we renamed localized product name
which I'll explain next.
At submission time,
we were blocked by the persistent productID error
and we couldn't find any way to clear it.
After several days,
we finally found a fix.
Just editing
the rejected products localized name
even just retype it,
reset the products and clear the error.
Finally,
we resubmitted
And
we finally passed the review
Thank you.
But there's still a surprise.
Surprisingly
Our backend showed no purchase activity.
how did Apple verify it?
The demo video? Or were we just super lucky?
We'll never know.
But the lesson is  clear.
Submit early.
Apple review process can be full of surprises.
After sharing
our implementation, there’s one more thing I want to stress.
Before the United States allowed external checkout links this year
they are actually some regions already permitted external payments
like the European Union and Korea.
In Taiwan,
In-App Purchase is still mandatory, but this global trend might eventually reach us
It's something we can keep an eye on.
To summarize the key takeaway
here's a checklist for anyone who wishes to use a similar approach.
First, coordinate with your backend about handling mixed receipts.
Filter purchases by productID.
Test both flows using the tools we covered earlier.
Leave buffer time  for app review process.
And
ensure your product  is available to purchase during the app review process.
The hybrid approach isn’t perfect
it adds complexity
but it gave us a low risk way to adopt StoreKit 2 for our new feature
The issues we faced were small,
but difficult to find solutions on the internet.
I hope this session saves you time
Before we wrap up, I want to introduce FanKlub
a brand new feature in the KKBOX app.
FanKlub helps fans feel a deeper intimacy with their idols
There are two QR codes on the screen
one to access my slides and another to check out FanKlub
And in case some of you want to know more about Tonku
here's her Instagram
And while you are all scanning the QR code,
I have a little wish.
As a first time speaker, I want to have a selfie with all of you.
Is that okay?
Oh, please,
come on, thank you
Say cheese!
Thank you!
Okay, a big thank you to  all the staff who worked so hard behind the scenes
And thank you for listening.