那接下來要介紹的是 vocus 的 Mobile Product Leader YC Hsu.
他熱衷於為創作者打造令人驚艷且具有影響力的產品
那，剛剛提到的，我們這場演講是以英文來進行的哦！
讓我們歡迎 YC，謝謝
Okay. Hello, everyone.
My name is YC, and I'm from vocus, which is 方格子.
And I'm very happy to be here as one of the speakers at iPlayground.
And a couple months ago, I went to Tokyo for the try!Swift Tokyo Conference.
And I was so inspired by all the sessions and all the people I met there.
So after that, I was like, what if I could share our journey of adopting TCA in our production app?
And not only for Taiwanese audience, but also for people from other countries.
So that's why I'm here. And that's why I choose to give this talk in English.
So I hope you guys enjoy my sharing and also enjoy all the great sessions during these two days.
Okay. So first of all, let me introduce myself.
My name is YC, or you can call me Yi-chin.
I'm currently the mobile product lead at vocus.
So I'm product manager now, but I'm also an iOS developer.
And I've been working with TCA for over one and a half years,
including a personal side project called Check-in Box and two production apps.
And I was deeply involved in building the whole foundation of our vocus iOS code base as well.
We are building product for creator economy,
which is we are helping creators to find their 1,000 true fans on our platform
so that the creators can publish their own work,
mostly are articles, engage with their fans and monetize their content,
which we call it 內容變現 or 知識變現.
And actually, we have a website, but we don't have a mobile app yet.
So we are going to launch our iOS app in Q4 this year, hopefully.
And of course, we are building this app with SwiftUI, TCA, and Tuist,
which is a Xcode project management tool.
And I will focus more on TCA in today's sharing.
So back to my topic today,
I'm going to share what we learned from building a production app with TCA.
And I would like to start with this simple question.
What is the difference between building a personal app and building a production app?
From my perspective, there are three differences.
So let me show you.
The first difference is the mental model.
So when it's your side project, you are the only one developer, right?
So you are the iOS developer, you are the product manager,
you are the backend engineer.
So you know everything, you can do whatever you want,
everything lives in your head.
But in a team, every decision has to make sense to someone else.
So you are not just writing code anymore.
You are writing the shared understanding.
And the second difference is the mentalibility.
When it's in your personal app,
you can hack everything to make it work today.
But in production, you have to write code
which your team can maintain for years, for long term,
not just something that works right now.
So you are building an app from quick hacks to sustainable code.
And the third difference is the feature complexity.
In a personal app, features are mostly simple.
But in production, everything changes.
You have more complicated features like payment,
like you have to do the event tracking,
which means you have more third-party dependencies
like Firebase, Mixpanel, or AppsFlyer, something like that.
So you are building an app from simple ideas to real-world complexity.
So making architectural decisions is never easy, right?
In production, architecture is not just about elegance.
It is all about survival.
It is about how we manage complexity,
how we avoid regressions,
and how we onboard new teammates without fear.
And that's why we started to look seriously at TCA.
So let me share our experience.
Alright, so why we chose TCA?
Here are three big reasons.
The first reason is the maintainability.
Because of the composable modules,
features in production apps become messy really fast.
But with reducers, we can break the features into small pieces.
And each piece has its own logic.
It is reusable, it is testable,
and of course, it is composable.
So it won't interfere with each other.
That means engineers can work on different parts at the same time
without running into conflict.
And the second reason,
which I think is the most important one,
is having a shared mental model.
TCA's core idea is the unidirectional data flow,
單一事件流.
So that means everyone on the team can see the same picture.
So when you look at the code,
it is very clear.
The view sends an action to the reducer.
Then the state changes,
and the view updates.
Even with some side effects, like API calls,
we can still see the result come back as an action
into a reducer again.
So everything is expected.
There is no guessing and no surprises.
And the second benefit of shared mental model is that
the new member can learn and understand the code base faster.
Even code reviews get more easier
because we all speak the same language, right?
So the discussion focuses more on the problem,
not on trying to understand how the code even works.
And the third reason is the testability.
In production, things change all the time.
So TCA makes it safer.
The side effects are clear,
and TCA gives you so many useful testing tools
for you to write unit tests.
So it makes the app more reliable
and save us from surprises later.
But, of course, TCA is not magic.
We all knew that there would be a learning curve
or some setup cost when you adopt TCA in your app.
So for us, every architecture comes with the trade-off.
So there's no single right or wrong answer here.
You've probably heard about the questions about TCA before,
like the learning curve is way too steep,
or there's just too much boilerplate code,
or isn't it just over-engineering for most of the apps?
And honestly, they are all fair concerns.
And after about, like, five months
using TCA in vocus's production app,
I think we have some answers to those questions.
So, what we actually learn from TCA.
The first learning is that the learning curve is steep,
but for us, I think it is not as steep as you might think.
And yes, the initial learning cost is really high,
because you have to learn what is the reducer,
what is scope, side effect, dependencies.
But once you get over that learning phase,
it really pays off, because the team can move faster,
and you can refactor in a safer way,
and onboarding is more smoother than ever.
So for us, that is a trade-off, which is worth making.
And if you want to learn TCA,
it is much more easier than it used to be.
Like these days, there are more and more
free learning resources available.
You don't even need to subscribe to Point-Free to learn TCA.
For example, if you are in Taiwan,
everyone knows 13 (Ethan Huang),
and he has a fantastic free YouTube series
that works through the whole TCA in a very friendly way.
And actually, I realized that
for most of the experienced developers like you guys,
it was much easier than picking up a brand new feature
from Apple's WWDC videos.
And by the way, I think Tuist is much more complicated
than learning TCA.
So the learning curve is steep,
but not as steep as you might think.
And our second learning is more code at first
and faster progress later.
At first, TCA might look like it needs a lot of code
to get started, which is true,
because you have to define the state,
the actions, reducers, the view,
and for some people,
that feels like overkill for a simple feature.
But in our team, we built a snippet
that helps us generate everything we need
for a new feature, and just in seconds,
including the reducer, the view,
the state, and the view action between them.
So when we need to build a new feature,
we don't have to start from scratch.
We just use the snippet and modify what we need,
and that's it.
So more code at first, but faster progress later.
And the third learning is the testing happens naturally.
We are not suddenly become more disciplined.
It is just because the testing became easier
and more natural, thanks to TCA's testing support.
So with TCA, the test flow is very clear.
The first step is arrange, right?
So in TCA, we set up a test store,
and then we send an action to that reducer,
which is a test store.
And the third step, we check the state mutation
after the action is sent into the reducer.
So this simple pattern lowers the barrier so much.
So we're just writing unit tests naturally.
And not only for unit tests,
we also use snapshot testing for data translation.
And in the future, we plan to snapshot
the shared UI component as well.
So we tested more just because it was easy,
so it happens naturally.
And the fourth learning is Tuist
make scaling module effortless.
We currently have like 25 to 30 modules in our code base.
It seems a lot,
but Tuist makes scaling modules very easy.
When we need a new module,
we simply run the Tuist scaffold
with our predefined template.
This creates a consistent module structure instantly.
And then we use the Tuist edit
to configure the dependency and build settings
for that module.
And finally, we use Tuist generate
to compose everything we need together
into a Xcode project.
And for us, the best thing about Tuist
is how fast it makes when we create a new module.
So in the past, adding a new module was a lot of ceremony.
You had to edit the project file.
You had to add target and tweak some build settings.
It took a lot of time.
But now with Tuist,
it is literally just one command and the module is ready.
And everything is defined in Swift code, not YAML.
So it is also easy to understand and read.
So everyone on the team can understand what's going on.
So like what we said,
even we have like 25 modules in our code base,
there are never a burden
because Tuist makes scaling modules effortless.
And our next learning is the composable modules
makes everything really fast.
For example, in our project,
we have like a login module
for sign up, sign in and onboarding process.
And we have a design system module,
which is for share UI components
and a content card module
for handling some complex interaction on our article card.
So when we need to modify the login flow,
we only have to work inside the login module,
which is really fast.
And let me show you another real world scenario,
which is the design discussion.
And the photo was actually just taken two weeks ago.
It was me sitting next to our designer
and we are discussing the UI bottom padding
in different devices.
So during the discussion,
the designer and I could literally sitting side by side
and we open the SwiftUI preview
for building only for that module
and fine-tune the design together in real time.
So because the module was isolated,
so you don't need to build and run the whole app.
The build and feedback loop was extremely fast.
So making the collaboration much smoother
and much more productive.
And not only for faster,
composable module also make previews reliable.
Like what QCL just said before,
if you tried SwiftUI before,
you probably seen something like this.
When you put SwiftUI views
and the external dependencies like Firebase
in the same module,
then your SwiftUI preview may be crashed.
But when you separate the SwiftUI view
from those dependencies,
the preview not only run faster,
but also avoid those crashes entirely.
So it makes the preview not only faster,
but also reliable.
And our last learning is,
when we ran into problems,
most of the challenges came from SwiftUI,
not from TCA.
So things like the reuse behavior of SwiftUI list
or some rendering performance
in complex views or complex animations.
And to be honest,
it was frustrating at that moment.
But I think it is part of working with SwiftUI today.
So like what we said,
there is no single right answer here.
SwiftUI give us huge wins
in development speed,
the consistency,
and the maintainability.
But when you need pixel perfect performance
on complex interaction,
maybe you have to use the UIKit.
So there are always trade-off
between using SwiftUI or not.
You might ask,
should I use TCA in my project?
So here are some suggestions for you.
The first suggestion is
to make sure TCA is a good fit to your product.
At least for now,
TCA really comes alive
when you use it with SwiftUI.
So if your current app is still UIKit heavy,
it might not be the right time yet,
but that is totally okay.
But if you are starting a new project
or a new feature,
or you are already using SwiftUI in your app,
then TCA can be a strong choice
in that environment.
And my second suggestion is
to learn by building something small.
So don't just jump into
and try to rewrite your whole app.
Instead, you can start with a simple side project,
maybe even something personal.
It gives you more space and time
to explore what TCA can do for you
and without pressure.
And once you've done something,
you can even share your work with others.
And there's a showcase discussion
on the TCA's official GitHub repo
where people post their works.
So I actually shared my first TCA project there
one and a half years ago,
and it was just a small project,
but it gave me all the foundation
that I need when I move on
to the production app.
And my next suggestion is
to cultivate your own best practice.
So don't just try to copy TCA by the book.
Try it, refine it,
and make it fit to your team and product.
And sometimes the right tool
might not be TCA at all.
Like Point-Free has many useful tools
like the swift-sharing
for sharing state management,
or swift-dependencies for dependency management.
What matters is to find the best practice
that truly fits your team
and your product.
So if you are curious about TCA,
the best way to find out
if TCA works for you or not
is really simple.
To start small and build something
and see what you've learned along the way.
And that's been one of the biggest lessons
from my years working with TCA in my career.
So that's all for my sharing today.
Thanks for listening.
And I'll be happy to hear your story after the talk.
Thank you. Thank you so much.