接下來這位講者是遠從日本而來,
他是LY Corporation的iOS Engineer,Yuki Aki。
Yuki目前在LINE負責改善Build System,
他經常在各大會議分享Swift的開發心得,
同時也是多個開源專案的貢獻者,
包含Swift Compiler、fastlane還有XcodeGen。
今天的演講他會以英文進行,
就讓我們歡迎Yuki Aki。
比起薄荷巧克力，我還是更喜歡Xcode♡
I'm surprised. What happened?
你好，我是秋，because my mother is Chinese, so I little know Chinese self-introduction, but only it.
Hello everyone, this is Yuki from LY Corporation.
In this talk, I will address the Swift performance evolution,
and how we as a Swift developer can approach it.
Yeah, that is not my introduction,
because I want to introduce Swift, not me.
Great. So, today's agenda.
First, I'll explain the Swift multi-platform support
and runtime behind it,
without focusing on the performance.
Next, I'll touch on the challenges of array,
explain the fundamentals of Swift performance,
through how array works,
and show how InlineArray can help address those challenges,
as an example.
So next, finally, based on all that,
I'll explain what's important for us to be mindful of
and to understand about Swift evolution.
OK, so first, let's talk about Swift multi-platform support,
its runtime and performance aspects that come with them.
Oh, I found it.
So, Swift has been growing into a language
with potential across many platforms.
Of course, it's a mainstream language
on upper platforms like iOS, watchOS,
visionOS, macOS, and tvOS.
It's also available on the other operating systems
like Windows and Linux,
and even supports web development paradigms
like the Wasm.
And experimentally,
it's also moving towards supporting embedded systems,
which are more minimum and have stricter environments.
Furthermore, an Android work group
has been launched in the Swift community,
and adoption for Android development
is also progressing.
As you can see,
the Swift supports a wide range of platforms
and continues to evolve.
When it comes to understanding
its multi-platform nature and its performance,
what we really need to look at
is how Swift works under the platform.
A Swift program doesn't run on its own.
It needs an environment that makes it behave as like Swift.
In other words, it's a runtime.
This runtime is called libswiftCcore on most platforms.
So,what exactly does libswiftCcore do?
As I mentioned earlier, libswiftCcore is a Swift runtime.
In other words,
it's a foundation that enables Swift to run on a platform.
libswiftCcore mainly exists
to support Swift dynamic features.
In construct,
the compiler handles the static side
like checking your code correctness,
performing optimization and building.
Therefore, the dynamic refers to things like reflecting memory layers,
performing allocations,
and managing memory
through the automatic reference counting.
The way libswiftCcore is distributed
varies by the platform.
On Apple platform,
it's bundled with the OS.
This is why some features
of newer Swift versions aren't available
until you update to the latest OS.
The benefit of having the OS provided
is that each application
doesn't need to include the runtime
and prevents upsides from growing.
For Linux programs,
you can choose to link the runtime statically
or include it as dynamic library.
Unlike on Apple platform,
without considering the OS version,
you can use the latest Swift features right away.
On Windows,
the current approach is to bundle it with the app as a dynamic library.
So on the OS environments we've talked about,
the runtime set up the Swift execution environment for us.
However, the runtime is by no means small
and in environments like embedded systems
where memory and storage are limited,
including if it's not practical.
So Swift allows you to build a program
for an embedded system
including a much smaller Swift environment.
This is called Embedded Swift.
Embedded Swift is an executables tailored
for an embedded environments.
By dropping some dynamic features to reduce binary size,
it delivers smaller Swift programs
suitable for embedded systems.
So how does the Embedded Swift stay small?
As you know,
Swift offers a wide range of features
and some of them are especially tied to runtime.
For example,
features like untyped throw, reflection,
any and weak require runtime metadata
and type information.
In embedded systems,
because environment is limited,
these features lead to runtime overhead
and increase your program size.
Embedded Swift provides a subset of Swift language
by removing such features
that would cause overhead in embedded systems.
Embedded Swift supports the standard library.
Features like codable, encodable,
and decodable aren't supported
because they require the reflection on runtime.
But most other familiar features are supported.
However, there are challenges
and one example is Array.
Swift Array is implemented
at dynamic heap allocated container
to provide rich functionality.
While it's safer to use than the C-style Array,
those rich features come with overhead.
Oh, I noticed that we have many Array talks today.
In embedded systems,
using Swift Array can be a costly choice
because that relies heavily on the heap.
So how can we overcome Array's costs
on embedded systems?
Starting with Swift 6.2,
InlineArray offers one way to address this challenge.
Let's look at what makes Array costly
and how InlineArray solves it.
Also, we can see valuable hints
about what Swift performance really means
from Array challenges
and how it's solved by InlineArray.
So let's dive in and take a closer look together.
Now let's look at challenges of Array
and walk through how InlineArray works.
This is a kind of Array call you all write all the time.
Let's see how an Array is stored in memory
when this code is run.
First, since Array itself is a struct,
it starts in an area called stack.
You may already know about stack,
but let's take a moment to review what the stack is.
The stack is a memory-efficient region
used for storing local variables
and function calls.
Data gets allocated and freed
in a strict, last-in, first-out order.
I'll explain later, unlike the heap,
it doesn't need memory management
with reference count.
To give you a clear image,
let's look at what the stack actually is
and with example of a real function call.
First, let's see how the stack changes
when we call this test1 function.
When test1 function is called,
the stack gets a new block data on for it,
holding the test1 function information
like its local variable.
Then, after running some code inside test1,
as you can see, it's called test2.
At this point, what happens to the stack?
Well, just like before,
the information for test2 gets pushed on stack.
OK. Oh, sorry.
I didn't know my voice is small.
OK, sorry.
Just like before,
the information for test2 gets pushed on stack.
In this way,
each function data is managed on its stack frame.
When test2 finished
and execution returns to test1,
what happens to stack?
Since stack works in a last-in-first-out manner,
it popped out from top frame test2
and freed the block.
By releasing entire frame at once,
all of test2 data is cleared from memory.
When test1 finishes,
it's popped and freed in the same way.
It's clearly releasing all data
from the function code so far.
When you set block points in Xcode,
your app crashes.
You've probably seen this screen.
This list on the left is called call stack,
which is the same stack I'm talking about.
Each thread has its own stack,
and you can inspect detailed information
for each one right in Xcode.
Array also follows a similar flow
and is stored in stack,
but internal implementation uses the heap,
so things are not quite that straightforward.
To our flexible addition and removals,
an array maintains an internal buffer.
This buffer is stored
in the separate area from the stack frame.
That buffer is stored in the heap area.
Let's talk about heap.
It's a flexible memory area
used for long-lived or shared data
like class instances.
You can allocate a free memory in any order,
but that means system has to keep track
and manage it.
Also, allocating from the heap
is slower than using stack.
I'll describe later about it.
Let's also check how the heap works
using a simple example.
Here, as you can see,
we look at code that works
with an instance of some class type.
First, the reference address
to the class instance is stored in the stack.
Then, the class instance itself
is stored in the heap,
and the address on the stack
will point that heap location.
When your code takes or drops
a reference to the instance,
some count updates its internal written count.
This mechanism is called auto-reference counting.
That counter decides
whether the heap object should stay alive
or frees when it reaches zero.
When it reaches zero,
Swift frees the object memory on the heap.
That's how Swift manages memory in the heap.
Auto reference counting
actually comes with a hidden cost.
Like behind your Swift code,
the compiler inserts the extra instruction
to update the reference count.
This runs every time a reference changes
and over time.
That hidden work adds up to the performance cost.
Another thing to watch out for
with heap memory is fragmentation.
For example, let's imagine
we store some instance in the heap.
As your Swift code runs,
objects get freed and allocated,
leaving small gaps scattered throughout the heap.
This state,
and where small gaps are left scattered around,
is called fragmentation.
Now let's try creating
a larger class instance and putting it into the heap.
As you can see,
the heap has free space here and there,
but there isn't a spot large enough
for this large class instance.
The allocator may have to scan from the beginning
to find a big enough block
near to the end for a long time
or fail to find it.
In short, heap usage can incur the overhead
from fragmentation and such for continuous space.
So putting data on heap
can introduce various kinds of overhead.
In limited resource environment
like embedded system,
that impact becomes especially noticeable.
Let's also touch on the overhead
involved when working with regular array data.
For example, when you add an element to array,
there still is potential for overhead.
Because array is expected to modify,
its buffer is usually allocated
with some extra capacity
beyond the current number of elements.
But when that extra capacity runs out,
it allocates a new larger buffer.
Then all existing elements plus the new one
are copied into a new buffer
and referenced from the array struct.
The old buffer is then freed.
From performance perspective,
it's worth knowing that
this kind of copying and reallocation
can introduce overhead.
So here's a pitfall of array.
Even if it's just a small fixed array,
so it still puts it on a heap.
In environment with limited resources like embedded system,
that become a cost.
And if array grows,
you've got a buffer reallocation and copying.
So the question is how do we work on this?
Here, let's take a look at a good example
of old C array.
A C array is basically a fixed length array
stored on the stack.
Since embedded Swift can call into C,
so you could call C language
because that works a lot of main elements.
But because it has no bond checks and cause unexpected behavior,
so ideally we just want to write it in Swift.
And that's a point of motivation
behind introducing InlineArray to Swift.
InlineArray will be stored stack
so we don't need to care overhead heap
for fixed size array.
InlineArray,in a way,
Combines Swift safety with C array performance.
It's stored to stack with no heap allocation.
Its bond checks yet still highly performant.
InlineArray also has benefits in iOS development.
Even on iOS,
the stack advantage are significant.
It keeps data on the stack for low-latency access
and it eliminates heap allocation
overhead in performance-critical code.
Finally, let's take a look at what we learned today
and think about what's important
for understanding Swift evolution.
Swift is now designed
with much platform use in mind
and we discussed earlier
it also has growing focusing
on performance consensus features.
To keep up with the Swift evolution
and truly understand it,
I believe these three things are key.
First, understand the motivation behind the evolution.
For example, code like the InlineArray we looked earlier
might not seem beneficial at first glance.
But every new feature comes with underlying motivation
or specific problems it aims to solve.
Without understanding these,
it's hard to see their value
or know when to use them.
By actively digging into proposals
for new Swift features,
you can uncover these motivations
and turn them into your tools
in your own power.
Next, understand Swift performance.
Swift offers many high-level conveniences,
but this sometimes hides costs under the hood.
So like heap allocation,
reference counting
and buffer reallocation.
Knowing where these costs come from
and know how they differ across platforms
helps you write codes
that's both expressive and efficient.
Finally, understand the mechanism of your code.
Please look at your everyday code
through the lens of performance,
asking, is this the right tool?
Am I using it correctly?
And could it be improved?
It builds a deeper understanding of Swift.
Finally, I'd like to share a few more sessions
that can help deepen your understanding of Swift.
These talks and materials are great resources
for keeping up with Swift evolution
and strengthen your knowledge.
I encourage you to check them out.
Thank you for listening.
I hope this make your Swift journey great.
謝謝