下一位講者是遠道從東京而來
也是 try! Swift Tokyo 的主辦人 Daiki Matsudate
他擁有 14 年以上的 App 開發經驗
目前從事從新創到公共數位服務的各種專案
今天演講一樣是用英文來進行
讓我們用最最熱烈的掌聲歡迎我們國外的朋友 Daiki
Hi, I'm Daiki from Tokyo, Japan, where I organize try! Swift, an international Swift conference
It's my first time back in Taipei since speaking at iPlayground in 2019
I'm happy to reconnect with many friends from Taiwan
Thank you to the organizers for such a great event
Today, I'll talk about identity verification on mobile devices
We prove who are using identity documents issued by public authorities
For example, this is my passport
It's an official document issued by the Japanese government that certifies who I am
With this, even here in Taipei, I can prove that I am Daiki Matsudate, born in January 31, 1991, and citizen of Japan
And this is Japan's My Number card, another official identity document issued by the government
On the surface, it shows my name, address, date of birth, gender, and identification number
But more importantly, it contains a tamper-resistant IC chip that securely stores this information, along with two digital certificates
These certificates make it possible not only to visually check the card, but also to electronically verify my identity and even create digital signatures
All of these are called identity documents, and identity documents are used to uniquely identify a person
It must be issued by an authorized organization, and it typically includes portrait and personal information, either printed on the card or stored in an electronic method
Now, this is a scene from a Netflix drama called Tokyo Swindlers, which became a hot topic in Japan
In this story, a certificate issued by a local government and a driver's license issued by the police office are used for identity verification
But in fact, there were fake documents created by swindlers
They even hired a homeless person to use a fake name and portrait as a property owner in order to say the land actually did not exist
This drama is fictional, but based on true events
In reality, document forgery like this has been a serious problem in Japan
To prevent such crimes, we need stronger measures, such as using IC chips to electronically verify identity, not just checking the card surface
Against this backdrop, many countries began exploring ways to store a driver's license on mobile devices, and in 2021, this effort was standardized internationally as ISO 18013-5
When the mDL standard was created, several key features were introduced
First is selective data disclosure of elements
For example, if all you need to know is whether someone is over 18 to buy alcohol in-store, there is no need to reveal their date of birth
Instead, the mDL can list only the elements that say age over 18
Next is cryptographic security
The mDL is structured in a format called C-B-O-R, which pronounces CBOR
The signatures are encoded using C-O-S-E, which pronounces COSE, which stands for CBOR Object Signing and Encryption
Some of you may be hearing about CBOR for the first time
CBOR is a type of date format
It has a structure similar to JSON, but while JSON is expressed, CBOR is a binary format
Because of this, data encoded in CBOR is typically 30 to 50 percent smaller compared to JSON
This compact size makes CBOR especially suitable for IoT devices and mobile platforms, where efficiency matters and battery life can be improved
There is also cross-platform interoperability
mDLs can be used over NFC, BLE, QR codes, and the internet, so they work seamlessly across different platforms
Privacy is also a key focus
No data can be accessed without the user consent, which is enforced through biometric authentications like Face ID or Touch ID
Based on this standard, Apple and Google have begun working with the U.S. states to store driver's licenses as mDLs in their wallet apps
Since driver's licenses in the United States are issued by each individual state, support differs depending on the state
In some states, they can use Apple wallets, in others, Google wallets, and in some cases, both
The standard for mDL was later expanded for more use with other identity documents
In 2023, this became standard as a mobile identity document, mDOC for short
For such as passports, insurance cards, and student IDs beyond driver's licenses, the feature is the same as mDL
Using these two standards, Our Japan enabled the My Number Card to be used on iPhones, starting in June this year
This was made possible through collaboration between the Digital Agency, the government of Japan, and Apple
It's the first case in the world where a national ID has been stored on an Apple wallet as mDOC
This card integrates both mDOC functionality and electronic certificates into a single device-bound wallet item
This digital credential adheres to global world ID standards, as I mentioned
Apps can access mDOC using APIs from Apple
These allow apps to request identity or age data within wallets, prompting user consent
I won't go into the details of certificates today, since it's specific to our local use cases
Instead, I'd like to show you how we can use Apple's API to retrieve an mDOC
The Apple provides three main APIs
Each is provided by the...
Sorry
Also, different contexts in app, in person, and in the web browser
So today, I want to be covering the third one
This was introduced at this year's WWDC session
It allows you to request an mDOC directly from the browser, even without an iPhone
Check it out if you are interested
So let's start with Verify with Wallet
Verify with Wallet is a method for requesting an mDOC from wallets within your app
The retrieved data can then be used directly inside the app
Because of this, using this API requires a special entitlement for app
The data is encrypted in HPKE format
And neither Apple nor Wallet can decrypt the information inside
Verify with... Oh, sorry
Yes
There are two entitlements required to call this API
The first one is In-App Identity Presentment
With this entitlement, you must specify which documents you want to access
For example, US driver's license or Japan's national ID
You also need to specify which elements you plan to read, such as name, portrait, or age
If what you request at runtime doesn't match what you applied for in advance
the API call will be rejected
The other entitlement requires you to specify a merchant ID
This merchant ID is different from the app ID, you use for Apple Pay or Apple Wallet
When you generate it from the Apple developer portal, you link it to bundle ID of the app
To use Verify with Wallet, your app must call the API and request the user's approval
Once approved, Wallet returns an object encrypted with HPKE
You then send this object to your own server where it's decrypted
After decryption, the payload is in C format
From it, you can obtain the elements you requested
The API provided by Apple is included in PassKit
In the descriptor, you specify the element you need
In the request object, you set the descriptor and the region
At this point, you also configure the merchant ID
When you send the data request to the controller
the user screen  a seed asking for permission to share the information
They will approve it with Face ID or Touch ID
Once the user approves, you receive an HPKE envelope, as defined in RFC 9180
This envelope combines public key encryption with symmetric encryption
providing a secure way to encrypt and decrypt the data
You then send this envelope to your server for decryption
When you decrypt this data, the resulting structure is C-Board
As you look into the data, you'll find that the given name field contains a value
This is the kind of data your app can then use directly
And that's Verify with Wallet
It's an API you can use for in-app identity verification
For more details, please check out the WWDC 22 session
What's New in Wallet and Apple Pay
I didn't go into details today about how to request entitlements or how to test with a simulator or on devices
But you can find all of this explained in more details on Apple developers' website
So next, let's talk about ID Verifier API
This API uses two iPhones
The reader iPhone sends an ID to the reader
The reader iPhone sends an mDOC request to the holder
and the user presents their iPhone in response
When the iPhone is tapped to the reader
NFC is used to initiate a BLE connection
Through this BLE connection, the mDOC is transmitted
The API provides two modes
display request and data transfer
With the display request
you can retrieve elements like portrait, age, and name
For age, you can specify whether you want the actual age
or just checking over a certain age
The requested information is shown on the screen only
Your app itself does not retrieve the data
No special entitlement request is required
As long as you enable the ID Verifier display capability in your app
you can use this feature right away
On the other hand, with data transfer
you can obtain additional elements such as date of birth
address, and sex on the top, the ones I mentioned earlier
Their elements are then transferred directly into your app
Unlike the display request
this mode lets your app actually access the data
That means you need to request a special entitlement from Apple called Proximity Reader Identity Lead
The ID Verifier API is provided through a framework called Proximity Reader
Compared to PassKit, it looks and feels like a much more modern API
Just like with Verify with Wallet
we specify the elements we want to retrieve
When we call prepare on the reader
we get the session needs for the request
Then we call the request on this session
The user is asked to present their ID by holding the iPhone for the reader
Next is a data request
It has almost the same as the previous one
but the difference is whether the requested information can be retained for a certain period of time
A small detail, but starting from iOS 26
we can use a protocol so that calls can be more shortened
With a data request, the response is strongly typed
so you can retrieve the data easily
In most cases, using the reader requires issuing a token
to authenticate the reader itself
This token is passed into the prepare method to be verified
This is also a raw data request
In addition to the standard data request
it handles raw mDOC data
but there is no time to introduce you to it at this time
I have shown you how to perform in-person identity verification sing the ID Verifier API
For more details, please check out the WWDC23 session
What's New in Wallet and Apple Pay
Just like with Verify with Wallet
details such as how to request entitlements
or how to test are available from the Apple Developer website
Now in Japan
the digital agency has released an in-person verification app
This app uses the ID Verifier API
Let's take a look at how it works in practice
Can I use the stand
Or somebody may help
Thank you
There are two iPhones in my hand
This is a holder
which has my number card inside Wallet
This is a reader
which shows installed apps to verify
In the app, select the use case what we want to get from the holder
Then tap Start
The reader shows the UI to be tapped to the iPhone
The holder taps the iPhone on the top
My phone requires passcode, sorry
Okay, this is my ID
The reader requests a tapped iPhone here
The holder has requested authentication with FaceID
The reader shows the UI
And it says I'm over 20
That's it
Let me recap this session
By using the ID card inside the iPhone
we can protect ourselves from more security and safety
Apple provides three kinds of APIs for the situation
In-app, in-person, and web browser
ID Verifier for in-person provides three kinds of APIs, display data request and load data request
And these APIs are compatible with ISO standards
So we can use three APIs even if published by US driver's license or Japan's my number card
or some new ID card in other countries in future
So that's all
So it was happy to hear and see you again
And hope to see you in Tokyo next time
Thank you so much
謝謝 Daiki 為我們帶來這麼精彩的演講還有Live coding
而且他還特地把 Slides 翻成中文
Thank you for Chinese slide
優しい
再給他最最熱烈的掌聲謝謝我們日本的朋友